hello and welcome it's December 7th 2023
we're here in active inference guest
stream
67.1 Andres Kata is here with us and
we'll be presenting And discussing on
ntqr Logic for noisy AI algorithms
complete postulates and logically
consistent error correlations so thank
you for joining Andreas and also yakob
and looking forward to this
discussion thank you Daniel thank you
for introducing me uh hello Jacob and
Jacob and and Daniel Jacob would you
would you like to talk about why you're
here uh yes sure uh so hi I'm yakob I am
a researcher currently based in
California um I am interested
in using physics-based principles to
model intelligent and self-organizing
systems and how different
Frameworks uh most specifically active
inference can be applied to both topics
in Ai and systems engineering and
broadly how we can use these formalisms
to understand systems at a deeper um
more inclusive level with other
disciplines as well and
I'm very interested to
hear uh your talk and your your thoughts
on
um these these uh these topics um and
engage in hopefully a productive
discussion looking forward to that
yes okay so I'm going to talk about the
problem of self-regulation for any
intelligent
machine
and in it has been a long journey for me
in dealing with this topic it goes back
to a pattern that I that that I took out
in
2010 but recently I've come to
understand it because I've been
collaborating with a philosopher and an
economist uh the aspects of it and
that's why I have this very Abstract
title for it called
ntqr because it refers to a situation
where you have an ensemble of n experts
to which you have given T tests and each
test has Q questions and each question
has our
responses okay so it's about evaluating
noisy AI algorithms when you give them
these types of testing
protocols and superficially at the
beginning we can take that testing
protocol to be the surface application
itself you are literally taking let's
say a multiple choice exam but I'm going
to eventually dislodge you from that to
understand that this is a digitizing
format for testing logical consistency
of anything right because you can
digitize anything so even if it's
continuous right you can create you know
four response ranges right and stuff
like
that and the big breakthrough for me has
been the recognition that for a long
time I talked about these things as
universal
thermometers and the universality meant
that they could be used everywhere just
like thermometers can be used everywhere
aside from you melting them right or
freezing them Beyond uh their
range and the thermometer also had the
notion of being stupid no intelligence
no theory about the world or the
phenomena that it's measuring the
temperature off and I've did that for a
long time and I took out a patent
because I thought that I had found a
method to do these thermometers and and
you can patent methods but it turns out
that I did not discover a method or have
a patent I discovered logical postulates
for
evaluation and so what I'm talk going to
talk about today is the logic of
evaluating noisy functions period in
general universally and so I'm going to
talk about them as
postulates because they apply whenever
you are doing these ntqr tests and so a
major conceptual goal for me is to
convince you of that right that I have
something that you could call postulates
because especially in the machine
learning world people say this is crazy
this cannot possibly be right how could
you have postulates uh for anything uh
in in in the real world uh so General
and you'll see that I I do that by
basically uh shedding all
representation so I I want to mention
these collaborators uh one of them
happens to be my cousin this is a
conflict of interest disclosure uh he's
a professor of philosophy at Virginia
Westland University and he has been the
severe critic of of things and I you
know I've done most of the work in terms
of the mathematics and the Machine
learning but he's the person that is
responsible for actual introducing the
the concept of logically consistent
versus logically sound and the utility
of of having any sort of logical right
proof for for anything that you do and
then the other collaborator with this
paper is IIA Parker who uh works with
the Navy and has a masters in economics
because you're going to see that this is
a fundamental problem in economics that
goes under the name of principal agent
monitoring
so I'm going to talk about you know the
the uh two main goals that I have in the
talk then I'm going to introduce the
main problem that we're going to be
addressing right this PR principal agent
monitoring problem and then I'm going to
make a a a some observations about you
guys I find that the the the format of
these live streams is uh incredibly
interesting to me intellectually and I
just want to you know sort of give an
outsider Viewpoint about what I'm seeing
that you guys are doing
that I find so laudable and as I was
saying to Daniel I have a little bit of
an impostor syndrome because I feel like
you guys made a mistake inviting a
stranger like me so suddenly but I I
hope to repay that kindness by engaging
in a good discussion with
everybody and so then I'm going to you
know introduce this idea right of
algebraic evaluation talking about
binary classifiers and I'm going to make
the math be really simple right just
linear algebra so that you can
understand understand it right I don't
want to lose you because this this is
eventually involves algebraic geometry
and something called grubner basis and
all these complicated stuff but I don't
want to use this math to hide from the
basic ideas that are behind it and then
I'm going to talk about what I said
before that that you shouldn't think of
the multiple choice exams as actually
being the surface realization of how
something is being evaluated you could
you could have given people a philosophy
exam and give giving them written essays
and then you have Chad GPT grade the
written essays and give a score right
from you know zero to four right so then
you're making an ntqr equals five test
right and so I'm going to go over that
and then the main technical result of
today the main thing that is the the the
Breakthrough is that there are complete
postul for pairs of correlated binary
classifiers that allow you to separate
Cor correlation from Individual
performance in a way that actually
allows you to then immediately trivially
sort of uh compute the only logically
consistent error correlation if you
believe that they behaved in a
particular way and I'll go through that
caveat then I'm going to show an exact
solution for the tree of error
independent classifiers and then then
show some experiments you know and work
work through the math of doing
it any questions or people want to
comment on
anything go a little further and I
believe we'll have a few pieces to add
in okay so the
the the main goal that I have right is
is that I want to describe to you what I
did technically right which is try to
figure out how I'm going to evaluate uh
ensembles of noisy binary classifiers
and so you you know it has a particular
way that I go about it blah blah blah
blah and you know that's sort of like
the surface realization but once you
realize how how I done it and what I
have been able to achieve what I really
want you to think about is this last
question right if it's not this thing
that I'm going to talk about
wow isn't it something like this because
it seems like this is so easy to
implement and it's so useful if it
existed and so that's where I want to
take you okay and so I want to have the
discussion for that and you know we can
go into the math and I can pull up the
papers I can pull up GitHub repos right
and I can show you stuff if you want me
to show it but I don't think it's going
to help the discussion and so I want to
talk about you know sparsity picking
best variants and safety from internal
mistakes that those are the topics I
think Jacob uh Rose you know talked
about some of them right I think uh the
November 14th talk that I saw with
Alexander he was harping very much on
sparsity being a very biological thing
and you're going to see how I use it
right because I basically have a data
streaming
algorithm
okay so this is my outside review I mean
this is a community of people that you
guys have been working in so such hard
problems and you're still working on
such hard problems which I have to say
you know and I'm being you know honest
here you've made very little progress on
right but it's because they're really
hard fundamental problems but you guys
don't give up you guys are still having
this live stream you're still inviting
people you're still discussing it right
I love that right not giving up on on on
on on particularly hard problems right
so I'm very attracted to that particular
mind
temperament and you're a community as I
can observe of people who have come to
neuroscience and biological things but
from different places sometimes from
physics sometimes from biology sometimes
from mathematics and have arrived there
but you're still bringing in people from
those places right and there's a lot of
active listening that I saw Daniel
writing stuff down right as people were
speaking I mean incredible stuff that
you rarely see so kudos to you guys for
setting up this sort of environment and
you know inviting a stranger like me to
talk to you it's very courageous
intellectually and I applaud it
and I hope to repay the kindness by
engaging a discussion for the purposes
of clarification right that's what we're
here
for okay so you know I I I I think in
LinkedIn now I have myself a scientist
and inventor and I'm starting I think
I'm going to flip it I'm going to say
inventor and scientist because the older
I get the more I think that invention is
better than science first of all it's
been around before us right and some
people claim that fire made us right and
we didn't invent fire it wasn't invented
by
homosapiens and so invention has been
before uh humans and it probably will be
after humans are around right and and so
I've done I worked in many different
things and so I I I've done I have a
patent for an underwater Periscope uh
you when you are at the bottom of a pool
when you look up you see that you see
that Circle that's called snail's window
the whole world the the the the whole
above surface world has been compressed
into that Circle and distorted but you
can see with the shading right that you
can pick up pieces of the world and so
if you could if you have a a polarized
camera You Could reconstruct
this so it's this idea of reconstructing
right what's beyond that's I find it
interesting and I've worked in in uh I
trained as a physicist but I trained uh
you know I I've been always interested
in the marriage of mathematics and exact
stuff with a very physical problem so
for my PhD I worked on super fluid film
vortices on a Taurus and I found a
theorem of reman that had had no
application quantum mechanics until this
problem okay so let's get to the to the
meat of the problem so the principal
agent monitoring problem so this is a
problem as old as a hell so it appears
in Plato's uh Republic and some people
call it the allegory of the Ship of
Fools right so there is a ship owner who
has a crew of sailors and you know
they're kind of Rowdy Sailors Plato says
that they may be drunk and among them
there's a philosopher king who's pler
himself right and uh and but the owner
you know doesn't know how to pick the
sailors right he he the owner just owns
the ship doesn't have any ability that's
why the owner has hired
Sailors so if you are an a a principal
and you hire somebody to do the job for
you either you're lazy or stupid and you
don't want to do it yourself so you have
this monitoring problem how do you
monitoring you know how do you do how do
you monitor work that you don't want to
do or don't or don't know how to do does
everybody get that the Paradox
there right and so and so Plato's answer
is democracy no way to do this right
because there can be
factions right part of the crew can have
a faction and you're not going to pick
the best Captain if if you have people
vote for who the best Captain is so you
know Plato use this to attack
democracy but this kind of goes this is
counterintuitive right we know that that
that group right that groups are better
for us right that ensembles help us
survive better
right so there's this tension in western
civilization between this sphere of the
mob right and this thing about the
unitary right philosopher king that's
going to be the
dictator so who's going to rule us is it
going to be the philosopher king
dictator or is it going to be the
mob right so there's this constant
tension so I came up with this problem
because I'm one of the hundreds of
scientists that have made speech
recognition possible on your phone right
now I used to work for Dragon Naturally
Speaking and Dragon Naturally Speaking
if you go into wir magazine and look at
the highlights of machine
translation uh the founding of uh dragon
systems in Newton
Massachusetts in the 80s is considered
to be a pivotal moment because you know
the the dragon systems went on to create
uh the first uh continuous speech
recognition product on the
desktop and and the way that speech
recognition was developed was as people
may know from machine learning was by
having data sets and one of them was
people reading the Wall Street Journal
and then that being transcribed with all
the mistakes that people made and the
hes and the H and so forth right but
after you know five or or or six years
you know the Wall Street Journal uh
Corpus became very important as a
benchmark and so people started
realizing well you know I'm being
greater in correct
in this transcription but I actually
it's the official transcription that's
wrong and so why don't we just redo it
right and so they went through the whole
Corpus and they redo they spent the
money to do it
better and so they so every test from
then on right in the software had the
old Benchmark with the mistakes so that
you could still Benchmark old papers and
then the new
Benchmark and I said who's checking the
new
Benchmark right it's the principal agian
monitoring problem right who checks the
experts how do we know that this last
transcription doesn't have any
mistakes then a second moment in my
professional life I'm a lecture at UMass
Amherst in physics right physics 101 I
have to lecture 500 students the only
way to do this is to give them multiple
choice exams bubble sheet answers right
that I then collect with the Proctors at
the end of the exam and take to the back
of the room and feed into an optical
scanner I won't describe to you
everything that I did and I was told to
do to randomize the test in the in in
the in the
room okay but it led me to sometimes
when I was feeding those exams to say
why do I need to feed the first sheet
the answer
key why can't I use the wisdom of the
crowd to grade the
exam and then finally the the thing that
actually got me into the mathematics of
actually doing this was in the in 2008 I
started working in in in uh in UMass
amher in the computer science department
with Howard Schulz doing digital
elevation models from uh multiple maps
that were done from aerial photographs
so how do you combine these things right
there's there's so much data now right
this is the problem that we have so much
data how do you combine it and not
prevent the noise from corrupting it and
then finally the 2010 patent by data
engines on error independent model
solution which as I'm going to tell you
has disappeared the the the patent is
not and void there can be no patents on
postulat you cannot patent natural
law so I'm telling you the the the
history of my business failure basically
okay so so this is the paper that was on
uh you know the the geometric
uh let me get the laser point there the
geometric Precision error right for
computer vision
test and basically the idea there is
that you you have a bunch of maps okay
and you and I'm I'm plotting here the
error Co variance Matrix between the
different maps and the way that my boss
Howard Schulz did the maps he did it so
that he took advantage of the fact that
when you have a photograph a and
photograph B when you match features in
a to B you can go this way right one way
an arrow but you can also go the other
way and that matching is not
symmetric so he wanted to take advantage
of that nonsymmetry to discover blunders
and he did so and he was able to show
that he got rid of blunders but he went
on to continue using the maps and
everybody told him Howard why are you
doing that those maps are really
correlated right that's A2 B and b2a
matching and he said yeah but why not
they have some information and So
eventually I was able to prove that he
was right and this is what I'm showing
here is is where I have a model where I
just assume that everybody's zero and
all and I've induced a signal if you're
a physicist you know what I'm talking
about right because I have these two
pair to these two maps that I know have
been correlated or highly correlated and
I'm introducing them there with other
maps that are not so
correlated so it's like Ian I'm I'm I'm
putting an injection right a modulating
signal and this recovery here was with
compressed
sensing and you see how without being
told that that along the diagonal
there's this strong structure it's able
to pick it up
up right so sparsity if the errors are
sparse enough you can discover the error
the Precision error between
regressors so even though today I will
talk mostly about classification
everything applies to regression
too and here's the the the Crux of the
issue right that that the the the the
way to do this is to basically get rid
of
reality this is the way that you get rid
of represent
ation right if if I have a model why
don't I subtract the True Value from the
model whatever remains is the is the
error and so I'm just going to talk
about that today in terms of
classification okay can we can stop here
if people want to ask questions because
the next theme is going to be data
streaming yeah I have a few comments
yakob you want to go first
though uh yeah sure I
guess I was wondering
if there if if you have been thinking
about I guess a measure to
quantify how uh how much information is
lost or can be lost when using a
particular
Benchmark uh because the way it it
sounded like when you were talking about
it is I guess similar to the notion of
well all models are Co graining of the
particular thing we're modeling
therefore every Benchmark is going to
have this problem of who's watching The
Benchmark or who's checking that The
Benchmark itself is correct um which is
a uh I I suppose in escapable problem we
cannot Escape it as a civilization right
nobody knows what the answer key
is right there is no dictator that we
can go to as a civilization as a society
it's
inescapable
right we're always benchmarking to
something else there is nothing but
benchmarking to something
else right am I am I crazy here or can I
get an alen right nothing but difference
yes nothing but gradient Unity is at
minimum to yes yes right that is the
only thing that we have to observe and
that's a statement of relative
relativity in physics too right that we
cannot observe absolute velocity we can
only observe relative velocity between
particles it's the same thing for
measurement it's not
different yeah a few other comments so
the back and forth keeping
the back and forth directions Being
Fit And how that contains information on
blunders like you described and then
another subtle pattern
is in the in the Matrix one slide
previously in the cells that were too
off diagonal yep there's a a slight
positive correlation that's
transmitted sply potentially Amplified
through compress sensing and distorted
and so
on there's also ripples of underlying
even trivially analytical Square
correlation matrices empirically Plus
noise plus compressed sensing have these
attributes and that is what puts so much
of the experimental design and attention
interpretation onus onto the cognitive
entity as hardly this or any data speak
for
itself yes
yes yes I have to agree with you right
there there is we have to distinguish
here there is no magic and there's no
metaphysics here there's only a
measurement which is a statistic of a
sample and therefore it's impossible for
it to for you to generalize
it right it's not an it's not an
intrinsic property here right if I'm
telling you that this is the error
correlation those Maps I'm telling you
that that's is the error correlation for
that particular collection and for those
particular maps not for the algorithm in
the future in the or in the past right
I'm telling you something about the test
that you just took period end of story
nothing else if you want to ascribe
meaning to that go ahead right but then
you're incurring that right that
cognitive uh you're the one who's now
becoming the dictator right the bucket
is stopping with you because you decided
to assume that that measurement meant ex
about the
world yes when you undertake the
epistemic quest then you're the
principal epistemic agent and that's an
N equals 1 situation another I think
interesting touch point is um
hierarchical predictive processing
models which we talk about a lot in in
active inference they have a highest
level prior and if that is going to be
also learned over updated there's going
to be a hyper prior on that so that's
one aspect where there's just the buck
stopping at a point from a hierarchy
perspective and then also um even with
just the gaussian the bell curve with
the mean and the variance but there's
not a variance on the variance that is
what gets collapsed that's the
metacognitive and that degree of freedom
is what constraints and makes models go
stale and makes them overgeneralize
without being aware yes and I want to
I'm going to address that one here
because I'm going to talk about
measuring error correlation independent
of model being able to measure empirical
error correlation now whether you want
to generalize that because you have some
view of how to basian generalize it or
not that's a separate issue right but
being able to at least Benchmark the the
the actual correlation on the test so
that then you can have those cognitive
models and those epithetic models that
can have that let's make the analogy
your car has a computer in its engine
right and it also has a thermometer what
I'm going to talk about today is about
how to build a thermometer that helps
the car's computer run the engine
better right and I'm all I'm saying
really comes down to that that it
wouldn't it be great if intelligent
Minds had a thermometer for
intelligence right because then the
thermometer just tells you that the car
is overheating it doesn't tell you why
you need a cognitive process right to
Fig figure that out oh it's because a
piston is blowing right or the oil went
down right that's a separate issue right
but knowing that something is wrong by
overheating with a thermometer is
golden right and I want to get to that
rock of having a thermometer that I
don't have to worry about
representation it just gives me a
measurement I'll deal with the fact of
what it means right but I just don't
want to worry about what that
measurement is or I want to reduce it as
much as possible so that EP so it may
sound weird but you would want a tool
that strips
epistemology from checking the logical
consistency of your
evaluation so that you can Aid that
epistemic agent and so I'm right this is
the thing that that I find weird and
fascinating here that I'm going to
propose to you that what we need to do
is strip
epistemology and I'm going to do that uh
you know continuing on and and so let me
now start talking about that
okay so data streaming so so you guys
talked about sparsity right so the way
that I encountered uh a data streaming
was with a good touring smoothing uh
algorithm in speech recognition at at at
Dragon systems they gave us a a a a book
written by
um gosh what how can I forget his name U
our research director and and he had
good touring smoothing uh frequency
smoothing can I get a count of how many
people know about what this is or know
what data streaming is is this something
that you guys know very well as a
community give a description that sets
it up for how you want to talk about it
okay so the the uh the the way that the
typical uh uh uh data streaming
algorithm and the way that it gets
presented is that it's a method for
minimizing memory when you want to
compute statistics of a of a stream and
so the prototypical simplest case is you
have a stream of numbers that are coming
down the the pike right and you want to
keep uh and at any moment I want you to
tell me what the average of those
numbers are
so the memory intensive way to do it is
to store all the numbers right and
whenever you a query gets made take the
average of those numbers right the whole
list but of course as the as the stream
increases right that list is going to
balloon and become humongous so the the
philosophy of data streaming is is don't
do that just keep two
numbers have a
sum so every time you get a number
increment the sum and then have a
counter of how many numbers you've seen
and then the average is just the sum
divided by the
number right so just having two numbers
two integer counters or two real numbers
whatever right you can
store and and at any time compute a
stream that may be a billion
long so that's the purpose of data
streaming right to
compress you you take a data sketch as
it's called which is a compressed
version of all the events that you've
observed in the data stream in all their
richness but you're not doing that
you're just taking the events and you're
doing some sort of compression on it and
you're keeping that statistic and you
and and then at the end when people tell
you ask you you say oh this is the
average that I've served so
far so for a good touring smoothing got
invented by Alan touring during World
War II because I don't know if you know
that he was responsible for the Enigma
machine breaking right in World War II
and you know they had they started to
you know Alan T was a very good
mechanical dude he actually built a tide
predicting machine way before computers
or he did any of the stuff that he was
doing you know uh as he's known very
abstractly right he was very much
Hands-On and he helped build a bomb
which were early computers that were
processing uh the uh German traffic that
day and trying to decode
it they had to work all day these bombs
were continually churning
right this is the nigma Machine by the
way recently found in a flea market
$15,000 if you find this machine so it
had these very complicated rers right
and so these These are the bombs and
they had a lot of uh woman assistance
right back when when computers were
women right before uh you had the grace
Allen and so forth right and so uh this
you had to send people home at the end
of the
day when did you stop you don't know how
many secret rer settings were done that
day when do you stop when do you decide
that you've done enough processing and
there's no big chunk of German traffic
that you've
missed so he came up with good touring
smoothing which was how many
rotors settings have we not
seen
which is a crazy statistic if you think
about it right what do you mean how many
things have you not
seen right and so he was able to do it
by shifting right by saying well there's
many orders for which we've seen only
one message right and there's fewer
orders settings for which we've seen two
messages right and so if you look at how
many messages were per rotor setting
which now biologist used to figure out
how many species they miss in a survey
you can then know how to shift the mass
to the zero frequency
observation you take a little bit of
probability from everything and shift it
down and can you believe that this is
still one of the probable best ways of
doing this estimating unknown
frequencies Alan orari from UC San Diego
has been doing some of the modern work
on understanding good touring smoothing
notably it doesn't get used nowadays in
neural networks because neural networks
never have any missing data they will
always give you an answer even if it's
wrong or lining this paper which was
published in neurs argues that that's
wrong and you should go back to doing
what he does but we're not going to go
into
that okay can I make a comment there
yes um this reminds me of the
distinction with parametric and
non-parametric statistics and when
people talk about how many parameters
this model has neural network
Transformer what have you it's a
parametric model that's why they're
talking about how many parameters there
are and nonparametric methods although
that's kind of like saying the non-
elephant animals kind of classic joke
it's also like a very open and
procedural space where there can be a
lot of methods such as shuffling and
leaving one out all these different
statistical methods that may have less
power or less of some statistical
positive capacity in the case where the
generated data for example are known to
be from a gussian error distribution but
under relaxed assumptions about variant
structure then non-parametric statistics
can do
well yes and in and and and heuristics
must be something that biological
systems use a
lot right instead of exact computation
I would mitos that statement into two
which the first statement I'm most
comfortable with is we can model
biological agents as using heris sixs we
can model anything as using heris in our
finiteness as cognitive modelers so if
we say we're restricting ourselves to an
eight parameter model or to this kind of
genre of model for this phenomena it's a
map territory distinction now as to
whether the territory uses here istics
whether you can really say does a
bacterium or does a squirrel use her
istics that is a question what are those
her istics but the first question which
I feel most strongly about is that we
can say that we'll choose to use heris
sixs in modeling complex Behavior why
not how can that
be not the
case
okay I'll grant you
that uh because I I don't have actually
experimental right I mean to be to be
precise right scientifically you're
you're asking for a particular
demonstration of our ristics and our
biological system and I don't have that
I only have an aspirational statement
that maybe it does happen
right okay so so the the thing that I
want to do here and the problem that I'm
trying to solve again is not necessarily
procedurally what's happening we know
that Us in the world are not completely
isolated from the world right but what I
want to think about is the ganking
extreme where you're isolated and
paranoid which does occur in certain
technological reals it doesn't have to
be a mental paranoia right so for
example a a self-driving car that wants
to check if pedestrian detectors
immediately right that immediacy right
means isolation right you can't wait to
get the feedback by actually touching
something right or get further
information moving forward forward and
you know it it's it's it's close right
it can only rely of on on its own things
because it's unlike a Roomba right it
can't be bumping into pedestrians it
cannot get feedback any other way other
than this mechanism that it's decided to
do whatever it is for pedestrian
detection which could be sonar or could
be
visual so I think of it as an extreme
that I want to solve to understand what
are the limits of what can be done okay
not because we are actually need to be
in that
real and so the I want to I wanted to
build certain features into it right
because I was using this in in in speech
recognition and and one of the things
that I wanted to do was you know to make
it simple and so I wanted to treat all
the members of the amples as black boxes
so I don't want to go inside your brain
I don't want to go in and get readings
of internal parameters in models which
is not wrong mind you again right to to
come back to the analogy of the
thermometer and the computer in a in a
car engine right you can have
intelligent things and and a lot of
people do neural networks right and they
and they inspect internals to try to
figure out right how to detect when it's
actually hallucinating there's nothing
wrong with that right but I'm saying
that it it itself is then going to bring
assumptions that I can't check right so
I don't want to do that I want to treat
everything as a black box I just want to
see what the decisions are from the the
the Oracle or whether that Oracle be a
person a function or whatever right and
I don't want to go I don't want a theory
of
mind the other thing that I want to do
and here's the The crucial thing right
is I want finite chains of safety
validation I don't want to use basan
models I don't want to use
probability because like you just
mentioned Dan those are hyperparameters
which are encoding information about the
world and the whole point about being
paranoid is that I cannot right I cannot
rely on that right I cannot rely on any
representational knowledge I don't want
to right to avoid that
Pitfall and so by going to sample
statistics that's how I'm going to avoid
that because I'm not going to talk about
distributions I'm not going to infer
anything about the future or the past
I'm just going to tell you a number
about something that already
happened and since it's a sample
statistics right I'll be able to then uh
do the magic that I do which is to
create a complete set of postulates so
then I can prove that you could be in
states that are provably wrong or
inconsistent and and so that's the
punchline right that that I can do both
of these things
of of being isolated and gonin right and
Paranoid by just having functions that
only use
statistics of the decisions by The
Ensemble members nothing
else let's stop here because this is an
important
point right this is a design choice
right that I'm
making Could you um unpack that a little
further I'm not sure I fully understand
how sample St using sample statistics
differs from conceptually from using say
basian probability on your
data so would would you agree that
there's the concept of sample statistics
and then you know distribution
statistics right and things like that
right that you can always Define a
sample statistics and actually compute
it if you knew what the the sample was
so that's what I'm talking about that
that that's what I mean by sample
statistics and then I mean
by so so what would it be it would be
something like um if if you have data
being produced by a gaussian
distribution right a sample statistic
would be the mean of what was produced
okay that has meaning that exists right
independent of what meaning you want to
ascribe to it whether you want to think
that it's the mean of of the actual
gaussian distribution right that's a
separate thing right using that data and
using that mean to then estimate what is
the mean of the gaussian distribution
that produced it is a complete different
task yes right so for one the data may
not have been produced by a
gaussian right this this issue just to
connect it to like what we talk about
with variational or just basian
inference and active inference let's
just say in the room
the temperature is continuously variable
but then the thermometer is going to be
integers and then the agent is only
capable of core graining into buckets of
10 so we can still talk about only cares
because of you know a Precision
Engineering spec right why am I being uh
uselessly precise
right yeah yeah variable
Precision to promote system properties
is definitely a corollary of this kind
of a framework more broadly like
getting getting rid of the um
representation question this is like
hierarchical predictive processing a
visual and so at the earlier lower
levels and this phenomena is
recapitulated in in silico as well as in
aspects of biological systems that the
earlier layers pick out less abstract
components like edges and on and off and
then not that it's clean but that at
each synoptic interval which can be
modeled as actually means and variances
and differentials in the hierarchical
predictive processing architecture that
can be modeled as like a kind of like
representation explained away you know
where's the romcom in this pattern of
neural activity and then it's just very
interesting that you brought up of
course the engineering setting
predictive code
which is to say difference in coding was
discovered SL invented in the video
compression setting and yet in the row
and Ballard 1999 work and so on it came
to be understood as a more general
property of how information transmission
and so
on in certain settings led to certain
parimon that has certain relation ships
with things like the cman filter and
predictive
coding so so so you you and Jacob have
mentioned this thing about uh a a
transmission of
information so so I I'm not going to go
into it there's so much to talk about
I've been working on this for a decade
it it the difference between the
observed
responses gives you something about the
test but also something about the
quality of of of the person who answered
the test
the uninformative person who answered
the test doesn't transmit anything about
how they performed the random guesser
only transmits information about the
test if I random if I randomly guess
what A and B are right I'm going to have
the right proportion of A and B as the
right as the test itself G to be in the
wrong
places yeah right but but but your but
you're transmitting the difference
between the A's and the B's and so there
is no magic here if the Ensemble is made
of stupid agents they are not able to
transmit via their aligned responses any
information that allows you to grade
them so my method has blind
spots right there is no magic here right
if your Ensemble is made up of stupid
members that don't have an information
you're not going to get
anywhere what do you think about an ant
colony where none of the nestmates know
about how many seeds that they have and
how many nestmates need what and how
much rain there is outside and the rate
of information and blah blah blah but
they don't know any of that they're just
using their local interested in that I
actually have a couple of books on ants
and an colonies and I saw that you wrote
a paper on on ant colony behavior I'm
very interested in thinking about that
but we're not going to be able to talk
about that okay fair enough
but okay so
I'm interested in the comment you made
about R too general information um the
so data streams as as ntqr test right so
we're going to look at binary
classification right so back down here
below we have the true label right so
this is a stream so think of this floor
to the right that gray box everybody
sees that Alpha and beta and then I have
three different classifiers that are
making different decisions right so
aligned on the first item the first two
classifiers are saying that it's beta
and the third one disagrees and says
that it's that it's
Alpha everybody with me on this as being
a right and so what I'm going to do is
just collect how many times each of
these different patterns
occurs that's the compression right so
we could be looking at a test that has a
million items I don't care I'm since I'm
doing binary classification I only need
two to the three eight integers so right
there we see the compress ression that's
very attractive right for in terms of a
biological system right because you're
not you're not storing the whole stream
you're just storing these eight integers
that are picking up these
patterns Okay and like I said and like
Daniel has said right you can digitize
to whatever you want in terms of
engineering spec you don't want to
measure the degree of the temperature of
a car to a millionth of a degrees is
useless right economically there's no
point likewise you may not care too much
to worry about you know knowing right
you don't care about too much Beyond
boiling or something like that right you
just want to be told hey the car is
overheating right you could digitize
that that's a safety you're coding in
there by
choosing the the the gradation of
digitation you're deciding what is your
engineering spec and what is your safety
concern okay so I cannot tell you that
this is an instrument that you have to
design and you have to decide what your
R
is any questions on
that yeah just a few notes this is
really interesting um there's the
principle of the hash
encoding or the kind of lookup table for
all the combinations and then you can do
hierarchical nestings um and then also
this situation is kind of like the cells
in the retina just speaking coarsely
that there's some false positive and
false negative for some activation
thresholds and so it's kind of like a
retinal
display that is getting noisy photons
and and also there's there's
variability through all of these finite
systems variability and finiteness are
ever prevalent but the observation is
just what it is exactly exactly and and
that therefore right all the problems
with philosophy and logic occur because
of infinity right if we just accepted
that the world is finite but maybe very
large right we would solve all sorts of
problems right zos axom choice is only
needed for infinite sets right finite
sets everything is is explainable and
understandable okay
so so here I'm going to show you you
know eventually you're going to see this
this this this is the the set of
equations for three
classifiers and these are the eight
frequencies okay and so the these are
the complete postulates for error
independent classifiers so I'm I'm going
to come back to this and make it much
simpler than it is right but I just want
to show you how you know these
frequencies here right there are eight
of them and I can sort of synthesize
right assuming that that that that the
classifiers have some sort of uh
performance right if I just I I randomly
pick numbers between one and 100 and
then divided by 100 to to have these
values and then I just plug them back in
here and then I get what what the
frequencies would have been of how they
voted so I I'm just trying to show you
how these numbers right are integers
right there's no probability
here and then the other thing I want to
go back to is is uh uh something that I
think you guys would find interesting
from the physic is Renault was a a a a
19th century French physicist very
famous for building the most precise
thermometers of his time at the time
when people were just inventing the
concept of temperature and people told
him how do you know that you're
measuring anything temperature is an
imaginary concept dude we don't even
believe that there's such a thing as
temperature and even if you did you
would need to have some sort of theory
about how you make errors in your
thermometer so that I would believe what
your thermometer is saying and ren know
was screw that right he says are you
saying that there is no science without
theory that there can be no purely
empirical measurement and he said no I'm
going to make purely empirical science
and so he was a radical empiricist
eventually in the 20th century right we
found out that empiricism doesn't work
but he basically is going to do what I'm
I'm I'm going to show you today and and
this is what I did with the maps he took
thermometers and just compared them
against each other that's all he did and
then he looked at the differences right
and he's the first one to start talking
about the concept of precision as saying
yes I can build the most precise
thermometers because I can get them to
agree to certain amount of figures right
and then they start
disagreeing so even in science right
there's a concept that you really do not
have science until you have this
agreement in
measurement you have to have error in
measurement if you do not have error in
measurement you're either tell me about
math and postulates or you're or you
you're you don't know what you're doing
your instruments are stuck you think
they have a prision that they actually
don't
have thank you this is awesome um
when we have multiple observations going
wide that's sometimes called Sensor
Fusion and then when we have the clash
of the prediction and the observation
and the differential that's found there
that's the predictive processing
architecture so those are both there's
so many motifs but you totally need a
minimum of two other otherwise you have
like a statistical monad which is really
more of just a pure conceptual object
and then one interesting tie in is like
in active inference as we specify the
generative model the preferences are
directly over
observations in the extreme case meaning
that the likeliest thing and the
preferred thing are one and the same and
it's just that it just you prefer to get
that number on the roulette table and
every single time your action is
confirming that's the
case that that is one special case that
can be set up as well as epistemic more
General epistemic activities but by
having the pragmatic value load directly
onto
observations like the thermometer
reading not I have a preference for the
room to be at 72 but I have a preference
for something about the measurements and
that is the direct Target rather than
the hidden State being the direct Target
which leads to a Fantastical
analysis okay so you guys seem to be uh
yeah yes ahead of about thinking about
this and how to implement it okay so let
me finish with this with the temperature
saying that that the reason I came up
with upon Renault was because that this
thing happens in invention all the time
right you're not too clever you invent
something and you think you're clever
but you're not right it's somebody's
thought about it before you just don't
know it right you're just ignorant and
so I said you know somebody must have
thought about this somebody must have
done something like this and so I went
looking for it and so I found this book
inventing temperature which has a whole
discussion about Renault and how he's
wrong because he thought that he was
doing a
metaphysics right he thought that he was
getting behind the
curtain that that was his philosophical
mistake right and so I want to pull back
from his philosophical mistake and say
no this is the comment I made earlier to
Daniel right I have I am not saying
anything about what the reality is I'm
only telling you an estimate of a sample
statistic that's it how you want to
interpret that is up to
you and I recommend this book because
it's great reading right because it's
about how you invent physical Concepts
right and and and the struggle that
people
went okay so now we're getting into the
uh the the the the part where I think
you guys are going to be interested
because I'm going to back go back
to the digitizing the format for logical
consistency because there's two
different viewpoints of the same
test and one of them which is the one
that I'm choosing to use the
ntqr methodology just to have a new word
for you to go somewhere else in your
mind is different from the ml binary
classification case which has semantics
and here's where I want to show to you
that the mathematics of the ntqr test is
separate from the semantics it can be
attached to semantics
but they're not the same thing so I want
to spend some time to make sure that we
capture this one
okay so and then the the payoff here is
the the realization that it you can
start to understand it in terms of
semantics this is something that a
machine could use to Binary classify
things in the environment okay which is
how I thought of it first and how people
in machine learning think of it right I
have a binary classifier because I'm
looking to classify things in the
external world I'm looking to be told
how many A's and B's there are in the
external
world but once I pull the rug from under
you I'm going to tell you that the
exactly the same mathematics can be used
to figure out the statistics of
correctness and that has nothing to do
with what a and b means in the
world because it just means that there's
some percentage of the questions had a
as the right answer and B as the right
answer but who knows where you came from
digitizing that format right so there
doesn't need to be any semantics
attached to a and b and I can still
calculate what your performance in the
total test
is so something that can be attached
semantically then has the same
mathematics in a way that it can be used
to check test
about
chemistry about philos phos ophy about
geology about any subject right you're
not doing binary classification you're
just correcting grades that a test that
have two responses per question or three
or four that's a general thing yes very
separate from the specific task of
binary classifying things in the
world so I'm going to stop and and and
and and encourage discussion because I
want you to get I'm going to show you
the differ es too in how it comes into
the the mathematics but I want to first
get if you if just with words you
understand that there's binary
classification where the percentage of
A's and B's in the test actually means
something in the world and then there is
grading of multiple choice exams where
the percentage of a and Bs has no
meaning outside of the test it just
means that that 10 questions in the exam
had a as a correct and you know 10 had
B but you know the questions could have
been about geology right A and B doesn't
mean
anything yeah just to kind of say it how
I'm seeing it if we look at the output
of a statistical test we might get a a
vector percentage rain and percentage
not rain basian calls a model
probabilistic statistical model percent
dog percent cat in contrast we have a
different procedural nonparametric
approach that can be designed
incrementally to dis discard various
aspects of
information especially in a discret
finite
space taking kind of the finitist
perspective on modeling and then using
that to say well I am cor screening into
this many cells so I am going to have
this many hash codes so we will be able
to do this in this
runtime okay that's a little bit too
complicated Daniel let me let me restate
the following we have a philosophy
question okay a philosophy
exam and and the and the and the
philosophy exam consists of uh you know
A and B questions right where you giving
a passage and you're giving two
philosophers and you have to identify
which philosopher wrote that passage
okay you you get the philosophy
exam yeah it's testing for familiarity
with philosophers not the ability to
generate philosophy or recognize new
kinds but I hear you right but but then
so so so we could have uh you know
schopenhauer and Vicken Stein as choices
A and B in question
one but question two could have Plato
and
Aristotle so A and B right are not
referring to the same thing in the two
different
questions that's what I mean by having
no semantic
connection right but your grade is the
percentage of times that you correctly
answered a when he was an A type
question right so is that is that make
it easier to understand that it I'm
making a simpler point right that I can
detach the cor grading you from having
attaching a semantic meaning to your
response it's it's like you um this this
is a common question in uh in
Neuroscience where certain cell certain
cells while learning a task can learn an
abstraction of of the task for instance
if it is a or b you will have cells that
respond to this concept of A or B but
then you have specific components of um
of the network which specialize to the
particular instance of A or B like
Aristotle versus Plato um or any
other set of um set of philosophers I
guess the question is
whether I'm not I F understand the the
what whether so both both can happen at
the same time right so both can happen
at the same time right you recognize
that that you can have the general
structure right where where basically if
if what I'm trying to argue is is that
if there's an algorithm that can grade
art equal two questions right then I'm
done right it can it can do it for any r
equal to question of philosophy or
economics and it can also do it for
binary
classification what do you think about
binary classification of language like
language generation questions or yeah
any anything right but but you would
have to decide if that's correct let me
let me go on maybe you know and then uh
when I show you things you can start
uh let me see if I can let me escape and
see if I can go now to
Mathematica so I get to show you some
pictures yeah yeah like the example yeah
I think of the pheromone perception in
the environment and the alarm or no
alarm is it at the threshold you got
finite number of antenna finite number
of receptors noisy signaling go no go
buck stopping with a nestmate brain
somehow some
way okay so let let let me go on and and
you'll see what I that I I think you'll
start to see how there's different ways
of looking at
things we still only see PowerPoint oh
sorry I see yeah I'm going to do share
again and I'm doing share now of
Mathematica okay you see the
Mathematica oops not yet
I just took it away I don't know why I
did
that you see it now
yes
okay and then
oh I'm G to stop the share because I
need to do the
whole thank
you that way I avoid okay perfect
perfect okay and then now I can go to
here yes perfect so this is the paper
that I sent Daniel and it's the one that
I've submitted to uh a special issue on
AI safety and philosophical
studies and so I want to you know so so
because I'm doing AI safety right I want
to I want to speak about this specific
case of doing a binary classifier to be
concrete right and so I'm now shifting
into uh getting you into the mode of
accepting that in fact they are there's
a logic to evaluation that there are
postulates and there's a logic and that
it's Universal right it's a big one it's
a big
Burber and so the way that I'm going to
do it is by just you know talking to you
about how I would what are the possible
grades on a on an exam that has two
responses uh before I see anything right
and so I know that if I have you know
Q uh you
know QA questions right of a type then
the number of correct responses so R is
for response right on the a questions
that the I classifier right does
everybody see that notation r a subi
right this has to be these relationships
have to
hold I claim these are
posit I you know I I've been thinking
how the hell did uclid do this to begin
with how do you introduce pulus what do
you argue what do you say right when you
have postulates you can't prove them
right you have to sort of say I can sort
of prove them here but you have to sort
of see them and say yeah of course that
makes sense Andres right you can't have
more correct responses of a than there
are a questions or B
agree we're within a circumscribed
axiomatic verified information
environment so play on where I have Q
questions right where I've told you what
the number of Q questions are
right there's no way there's no there's
no other way right and so therefore I
can I can immediately go and write you
know this this table I mean this is how
simple it is right I'm going to tell you
here let me let me make that
bigger right so you see this I'm I'm
having a a q equal 20 exam right 20
question
Sam and I'm just going to make a table
of all the possible correct a responses
you could have AA right the number that
you of A's that you correctly add said
that it was a and the number of B's that
you correctly said were BS and then I'm
just going to keep track of the number
of A's
right questions well the number of a
questions can only go from zero to the
total questions
right and then once I decide that
there's n a of them then like I said
right my correct responses can only go
from zero up to that one and then if I
have any questions the B questions has
to be this
Remnant and so if you just do that this
is this is the cube you get this is what
you get for the
grades until three weeks ago I've never
seen this Cube and it's amazing that
this cube is it's actually you know kind
of a nice figure right it has got this
double edged kind of thing right but
that's it if you answer a 20 question
exam with 20 responses your correct
grade is somewhere is a point somewhere
here is it a true
tetrahedra I I don't know what to call
it right it's got that 90 degree twist
right at the bottom is 90 degrees to the
top yeah well wow what do you see in it
what does it mean to you well the the
thing about it that that that I found
really interesting is let me show you
the other way of looking at it right
which is now the way that I looked at it
for years until this
year which is the the realm in which I
looked at it which was the the the
machine learning where now I'm telling
you what is the percentage of things
that a that you got correct I'm telling
you the percentage of B's and then I'm
telling you the percentage of of
A's and in that Cube that same Q equal
20 test this is how it
looks see how different that
is see how it has that kind of quadratic
structure what's different between the
two um now okay so I'm going to show you
what's different is that I decided to do
the math in the machine learning world
where so so this is what I'm I'm I'm
sort of showing you now right these are
postulates right the number of a
responses that you give me are equal to
the number of a responses that you got
correct plus the a the B's that you
incorrectly label as A's yeah true
positives and false positives exactly
exactly right this is these are
postulates right these are prior
postulates right they they exist before
you see any observation about the
test right everybody on board with the
fact that this is posets right and and
that the number of responses you give
right in a sort of a election Integrity
right there can be no more votes than
their voters it obeys this and I can
rewrite this in terms of being a binary
classification with these equations down
here yeah just to kind of connect that
to the case of an election so it's like
one approach would be to take in the
samples as evidence and try to estimate
a a continuous hidden State and you're
always going to get into this
statistical approach versus treating the
fundamental finiteness we
had I'm not going to use the ntqr but
those are the parameters that describe
the
finite Printing and dissemination
project of that project in that printing
there was a thousand ballots with five
options that is the state space you
could go into cognitive modeling you
could do narrative information you could
do interpretation you can have this all
the things but the finiteness and the
discreetness then to get around this
challenge of like well temperature like
in it could be like any number or it
could be a number greater than zero so
how do you deal with that and you take a
kind of engineering approach here which
is you define the safety zone which can
be hierarchical abstract safety zone
generalized anomalies and so on but you
define the safety zone within the safety
zone you have the direction of free
energy
minimization statistically control or
you just stay in this in the fully
finite worlds and maybe the issue can be
resolved by explaining away the
semantics of the
decision through mere propagation and
procedure exactly logical
consistency okay so so so it turns out
that the that so so these two parets
right these two parcs here are written
as a binary classifier here and you see
that these equations are linear here
right so that's the cube that you saw
with the planes and you saw that when I
went to the ml I showed you parabolas
that's a
quadratic are people seeing that in the
equations right that when I change to
the ml point of view where I'm dividing
right then I end up having these
quadratic structures right in the in the
cube right you see the the
parabola what does that represent to you
that's the ml space that's where I'm
telling you the accuracy as percentages
you see the percentage of you you got
half yeah it has the this this test has
the highest resolution when the coin is
even 50/50 statistics does the best job
when the coin is 99 and one then three
measurements give you very poor
statistical power because you can't
resolve 991 from like 982 very well it's
not quite like that but it's close to
that but let's move
on okay so so so this so so I'm not
going to show you the math but these two
equations right this is where the
algebraic geometry comes from this is
what we can observe right we observe how
many times you said that it was a and we
can observe how many times it was B that
you said that it was B and I know it's
related to your individual performance
by these this these equations it turns
out that you can disentangle them and
there's actually you know because these
two frequencies have to add up to one
there's only one postulate and that
postulate is being represented here in
the two different ways it's either this
one or this one either in the ml world
or the the ntqr world and here's where
we come back to that thing about
transmitting information the difference
between your responses is telling me
something about the difference in your
correctness just to clarify like you use
a single equation number 16 you're it's
exactly the same test it's exactly the
same test but I'm showing you know p p
of a sub a is RA a a ided QA so are you
co- asserting these auma or are you
declaring them equivalent they're
equivalent and so they're Co asserted by
equivalence yes and why do the shapes
look different then because they're in
different spaces one is in the P space
and one is in the in the integer space
right one is in the integer ratios and
the other one is in the the whole
integer okay you got yes so it's kind of
like a discrete mesh and it's continuous
and there's Integrity between the
discret and the continuous and you have
very strong procedural guarantees on the
discret and then you have arbitrary or
standard statistical guarantees on the
continuous but my problem is that I I
have difficulty seeing how a biological
system could do the division one but I
see I can see how it could do the
integer one very
well right that's why I'm bringing up
the ntqr that's why I think you guys
would be interested in it because the ml
space is not I don't see how a
biological system could be dividing one
but I can see how a biological system
could build build a cube that's 20 aside
it yeah that's kind of like a synapse
and the synaptic release it's in
vesicles like it's not like dopamine is
a continuous variable at the synaptic
level the dopamine release is in one
bucket
yeah so then so so then we get to the so
so this is the the the the interesting
part right so so what is the problem
with
ensembles gosh if we could just do so
here's where we go back to humanistics
right and my love heuristics majority
voting is such a great algorithm it's so
simple right it's so simple and it works
if if if things were good enough
majority voting would just be good
enough right it would just make us safe
as it is the problem with majority
voting is that it can go wrong right the
mob can be wrong
right things could be flipped right in
terms of their accuracy so we need to
consider now ensembles right and and and
the problem with ensembles is that they
can be error correlated right they're
not going to be making their their
errors independently so we need to
handle that and so here's where we come
to the first set of what I would call
non-trivial posites right because this
is what makes them complete right that
if I observe two
classifiers this right they can only
vote four different
ways and there's no other way that's it
that's the
completeness this is guaranteed so if I
give you equations that describe these
four different frequencies and those are
the going to be the four posites I'm
done and so uh by the way these are the
surfaces for some of the uh those
planes um I'm going to show you later
let me move on to the because it's going
to be
4:30
um so here's the
correlation so this is what I'm I was
saying before Daniel that this is the PS
right are these things right the
responses divided by the total number of
questions right so either I can talk
about RS or I can talk about PS and then
correlation is defined as something that
looks exactly like you would Define it
for distribution but it's here defined
for a
sample
right so basically what I'm saying is I
want to continue to write things as
being individual products of
performance and so what I really want to
have inside this parenthesis right is
the number of times that they both said
that it was a and it was a well that's
this number
here but I'm not going to put that
number right what I'm going to do is I'm
going to stubbornly stick with
individual performance and then I'm
going to put the difference between that
number that I need and what I and and
this thing that I'm stuck with putting
in which is the
product and so these are the four
postulates for pair correlated binary
classifiers you only need two of them
you need one for the a label and you
need one for the B label and it acts
exactly like you would expect uh
correlation to do right when when the
when correlation is positive it's going
to increase inrease the number of
responses where they agree and when it's
negative right it's going to increase
when they
disagree it has the right sign basically
right correlation here is plus
contributing plus and in these two
equations where they disagree is
continuing with
minus yes something like a finite
procedural recasting and reimagining of
the true positive true negative false
positive false negative those are four
actual values and so again within the
finiteness of digitized sensing
especially you can take purely
non-parametric purely algorithmic purely
arithmetical
numerical
approaches rather than always passing
everything through the kind of
statistical meat
grinder
I'm done I'm done Daniel I'm done I'm
done you you said you said exactly right
this is this is the the thing right and
so I'm not going to go back into Tom
Mitchell and platonus one of the
students came up with an independent
solution which is wrong and and I've
been slammed by reviewers because they
say they they did it right and I'm doing
it wrong and it turns out to be the
other way around but I'm not going to go
into that that's my personal beef but
let me then show you what happens when
you do when you take these equations
right so so what is the problem the
problem that everybody's encountered
with with pair binary classifiers is
that correlation is entangled with
individual performance in every one of
these equations do you see that 26a 26b
26 C and
26d have correlation in every single one
of them we cannot separate correlation
from Individual performance but if you
use algebraic geometry you can and
that's what I'm not going into you can
separate these equations you get back
the individual equations 33 a and 33b
are exactly the same equations that I
showed you
before but then you get these new ones
where you've decoupled
correlation so 33d 33e and 33 FS are the
only ones that have correlation and it
turns out that they are the same
postulate you get no
information
from them so uh and in fact then
everything in binary classification is
controlled by this number the number of
times that you agreed in the B label
minus the product of times that you said
there was
B it turns out that you can prove that
for binary classification this is
exactly the same as this other
quantity and the way that I'm going to
use error correlation is this one this
equation right here
and the only thing I want you to note
about this equation is that it's linear
in the
correlation so if you tell me what you
think the greatest and I observe how
that you voted and how you differed in
your voting I can tell you what your
error correlation
is I'm raising ahead and I'm just want
to show you some evaluation
okay
so
so see what
the so this equation is the solution for
the
prevalence of uh
A's when they do a classifiers are
making
error independent uh
mistakes it comes from this quadratic
polinomial that you get from
solving that very complicated system
that I show at the
end so now I need eight of them I need
three of them right so I need eight
equations so now I have I i j and
k and you see sort of a descending a
symmetric pattern right this lather goes
down one way and it goes up the other
way these are the B's and these are the
A's when you solve that equation you get
a
quadratic and it's that quadratic that
I'm excited to show
you right this do you get a quadratic
equation which has these complicated
factors that depend only on the stat the
statistic that you have observed there's
no free parameters so this is not basian
estimation in any way right you cannot
you have no Freedom
whatsoever so then when I do synthetic
data where I I've made it to have 19 20s
of of one of the variables it it
predicted uh exactly but let me show you
some experimental results and and the
one that I want to show you is where it
fails that independent solution is going
to fail if if the if the if the
classifiers are too
correlated it's going to give you an
imaginary
solution imaginary can I make a comment
on
that yes please sorry go ahead an
imaginary solution means that the
parabola doesn't touch the
axis and gosh I look at this picture and
I go I can draw this
circuit I can make this circuit physical
circuit right so that I could because
right I could make a geometric
construction that draws a a that draws
this Parabola and then I can check to
see whether electrically it touches that
axis and this is a warning light if you
don't touch that axis your classifiers
are correlated too
much right the error independent
solution has failed so this is something
that no probalistic method can do
right no probalistic method that assumes
error Independence can show that the
error Independence assumption is
violated that's the main problem with
distributions and statistics right if
you make
assumptions you cannot prove right
because you're you're you're tuning your
parameters to satisfy your assumptions
but when you're doing things
algebraically like I'm doing here there
is no
freedom you can be in a state where they
the and and actually I can show because
I can have a complete representation
where I include all the correlations I
can
prove that when I do these
computations if the classifiers ever
have a square root that's unresolved
this is the independent algebraic
evaluator I can prove that that means
that that set of classifiers is actually
correlated it has nonzero Z correlation
and Below you're seeing that that's in
fact the
case right you're seeing that one of the
the the the correlations is almost
6% and I've been able to detect with the
independent solution that in fact there
is nonzero correlation because I have an
an unresolved square root that doesn't
make any sense right these are integer
numbers what does it mean to say that
that you're you got a percentage that is
some square root
right and this cannot be done by any
infinite statistical right this is the
the distinction I want to make there's
finite statistics which is about samples
and there's infinite statistics which is
an infinite number of samples right and
there is finite statistics where you
where you accept that what's gold is the
sample the sample is true everything
that that you derive from it is is not
possibly true versus the infinite
statistical world where the world the
sample is always
wrong right in statistics a given sample
is always
wrong right the equality only occurs on
the average of the
samples that's a complete different way
of thinking
yes and I say that the finite one is the
one that I want to choose in terms of
safety and it's 4:30 exactly so I'm
gonna stop because you know I think I
feel like I've been talking too much and
and maybe people can chime in and and
push back and have interesting
questions yeah anyone in live chat and
then yakob go for
it yeah it's um
I want to show you how I just want to
say how crazy this is I'm giving you
error correlations which are the only
logical consistent error correlations
once I decided to do majority voting or
not and here I'm showing you that
majority voting is kind of like a little
bit too hysterical it thinks that
they're 25% correlated and in fact
they're only at most 1% and and so my
method right of using the postulates
gives a better
self-consistent solution I haven't gone
in into that right but I go what
basically what I do is I take this
number which is not at all an integer
ratio right and I find the integer ratio
that's closest to
it right and then I ask for that integer
ratio what is the
only logically consistent error
correlation and I get this these numbers
yeah that reminds me of the finite Pi
like 22 over 7 is a classic small
approximator of Pi and you can go into
finite
approximators exactly and therefore get
closer and closer incessantly keeping
the strong guarant right but at some
point it's useless you're you're you're
you're doing the the the width of a
hydrogen atom as people like to point
out right your error in the
circumference is going to be the width
of a hydrogen atom who cares
right and so a finite heuristic is going
to do it very well sorry Jacob I I had
to I had to interrupt you there to just
to point out right that that that the
fact that I can even measure error
correlation and say that it's logically
consistent is incredible I just have to
say
that yeah and no worries I I'm still
trying to wrap my head around the the
concept of disentangling the semantics
from the particular tools that you're
using right um because I feel like it
also kind of depends
on your
expectations as the person using these
tools like going back to the going back
to the example of Like A or
B like if you if you take away um if you
take away the particular content of
those of those questions and you only
look at the statistics of the of the
answers of correctness I would say
statistics of correctness statistics of
correctness then perhaps you perhaps you
are taking away the correlation from the
particular content of those questions
yes but are you taking away the
correlation of for instance the person
who said those questions oh my God it's
so good it's so good that you were
saying right so so so so here's what I
had to do at UMass when I was giving the
the exams right so so UMass amher is a
state school right so you get bubble
sheet answers right uh exams at at at
UMass amher right but I taught at
Williams and at swore right I never gave
bubble sheet exams at at swore or
Williams right so it's only right that
when you have large classes that you
have these things right and so at UMass
right that the students would
cheat so they told me you have to make
five exams and
Dr the student is one color exam and
then you put you see people in a diamond
pattern around around that
student so that everyone around the
student has a different color
exam and then you scramble the the the
responses so nobody can uh look over
anybody's shoulder and copy the
bubble right so what am I trying to do
there why am I trying to do that because
I want to prevent the error correlation
that occurs because you cheat
it and I'm trying to find out the error
correlation between all the students
that is due to a commonly shared
cognitive misunder understanding of
Newtonian physics maybe they're still s
right maybe I put a question that is
testing their their belief in
Aristotelian physics right and I want to
detect that that and so when I get a
wrong answer in a question the purpose
of the exam for me as a professor is to
find out what I should be talking about
the next class right to address the
mistakes that people are making
cognitively I want to design a test that
blocks any error correlation except the
cognitive
one and so that goes to what you're
saying Jacob right you get to decide
what error correlation right somebody's
error correlation right may be a goal
for you right I as a teacher want to see
cognitive error
correlations because I want to help you
and teach
better and the when I talked about
digitizing you you brought up another
thing Jacob which is that maybe in the
original signal the responses were not
correlated but then when I digitized it
I
correlated I have no and and I think
Daniel also talked about that right that
when you change formats right you
introducing spio
signals and all of them are in
there and yes there is no guarantee
right but but by the way uh there is the
advantage here that I can measure the
error
correlation right so that you can see
whether I did introduce right by
digitizing the te the The Logical
consistency of your
grading if I introduced correlations or
not that existed in the original format
does that make
sense there's no free lunch there's no
free lunch you won't get anything for
free here if you really think about it
right it sounds magical but it
isn't it's okay on the free lunch theme
kind of thinking about this in a fun way
there's a lunch where you just show up
and it's there for
you so that's kind of the dream scenario
if you're one of those who eat lunch at
that time because it's kind of like
you've chosen the access to create a
finite projection to you've the it's the
right test the seating
arrangement there's just an ideal
situation and then some of those may be
actually perhaps even relaxed in
practice like I I I don't know all the
details but when you describe that
you're taking an integer
approximator so there's ways of of in of
integer iing and
ftiz that strip semantics but then I
thought about what if the Ship of Fools
what if none of them can be the captain
well then the ship's going to go extinct
and then it doesn't matter what that's
the imaginary Parabola that doesn't make
contact it's like no there's no decision
rule there's also no quadratic
regression but this is just an imaginary
solution these people are talking about
survival strategies that are imaginary
yes yes yes so so so you get the other
part about which is what why it was good
to put it in a philosophical uh Journal
which is what if there is no answer key
what if we are all
deluded and we're just testing with a
test our alignment on a delusional
belief I explained this to uh an ex-wife
of mine who's a psychoanalyst and she
because I was explaining the concept of
logical consistency versus logical
soundness by the way with logical
soundness you need to know the truth
table logical consistency you don't
you're just checking to see right
without semantics that you're that
you're uh cranking the logic Machinery
correctly right if your premises are
correct your conclus Solutions are
correct so that's what I mean here by
logical consistency of grading right I
cannot tell you exactly what the grade
is but I can tell you whether you're
being logically consistent with how you
believe uh your your experts are
behaving right so that that is
yes that's the only thing that can be
checked here right but it can be
provably shown right that that you are
in a highly correlated State and
therefore you should raise alarm and and
so when you look at at that what it this
could be it could be also you could
think of it as a way of selecting right
if you have different models and you
find the one that's most aligned with
the what your beliefs are about what the
truth is then you have instant
compression right just select that model
right because you found the one that's
most aligned with everybody right and so
you don't need to keep all of them but
there's nothing to right to say that
you're not hallucinating and that you're
going to be eaten right because you
think that there is no tiger there but
there is a
tiger right you could have false
beliefs and be delusional right
confident and alive not confident and
soon to decease exactly right and so
there's nothing here that prevents that
from
happening but it would allow you if you
were initially in a good operating state
to start detecting something that is
malfunctioning right so could prevent
that from
happening yeah I'll ask a question from
the live chat upcycle Club writes I have
a question how do you define the data
sketch of the
decisions so that was in the uh that was
in the uh the the statement about
completeness right so whenever you look
at an
ensemble uh there by the way there's
there's a if you know data streaming
right there's data streaming algorithm
for every statistic right sample
statistics there's many of them of
course for a finite sample there's only
a finite number but there's many of them
right combinatorially
explosive so here it is right if I'm
talking about three right I have to talk
about two to the three or eight
different
frequencies if I'm looking at only their
alignment right but that's not the only
statistics I may want to right suppose
that you're looking at classification of
of uh DNA
payers so you're woring so there's also
sequence
information so you may want to know how
accurate you are on the point you know
on the on the given base pair but you
may want to know what what what
percentage of times you were correct on
both
pairs so now you're keeping tab of
another set of Statistics which is not
the one here in equation 38 right
because now you're comparing uh two
different points on the DNA sequence
right and so you could be keeping
statistics about the observation
10 steps back or 10 steps forward right
so there's an infinite number of
Statistics that you could be doing so
I've only shown one small set of them
and for every one of them you're going
to be able to write this summation right
it's it's it's it's a part of uh if you
will of of the basis of probability
theory that you have event space right
and that you can delineate event space
completely right so you have
completeness right there is no event
that you do not know about if you and by
the way there's no theory about all the
theories of the world this is why you
cannot do this with theoretical work
right because we do have no theory that
can enunciate all the postulates of all
the possible theories about the
world this can only be done with sample
statistics right that's how I get away
with this yeah to to kind of reflect
that back I I first off I again I
appreciate this presentation and work I
I encourage people to to look into this
because it's very interesting and to
connect to the prior Century of
statistics and understand where exactly
this is positioned and and How Deeply
this statistical Paradigm is baked into
the safety discussion and to this last
point that you're creating many possible
finite
spaces um the error patterns and
covariances can be harder to fake than
the mean you could just take one number
say God
Dan oh my God Daniel oh my God okay you
oh my God I mean I mean come on it it
just yes exactly right right you can
fake the signal but you cannot fake the
correlation it's so much harder right
it's so much harder to do
that yeah if they're faking the mean and
the variance and all the higher
coordinates emotion then it's in
distinguishable exactly exactly right
yes so this applies to the concept of
Enemy Inside the gates how would you
detect that something inside of you is
hallucinating right now and you
shouldn't be paying attention to it
right this is would be a crucial thing
for any right let's go back to the
original question right forget about
what I said if it's not how I said it is
it has to be something like this is how
can an entity have intelligence have
integrity of thought if it doesn't have
a way of detecting Enemy Inside the
gates
yes you have to defend against
yourself cognitive
security yes right this is this is what
I think is so interesting about this
right right forget about right the
number one enemy you have to worry about
is you your hallucination that is
preventing you from seeing the
tiger that I would think that that would
be the primary thing and like going back
to the semantics I can see how this can
be used for binary classification of
right o of safe unsafe right tiger not
Tiger but then because the mathematics
is exactly the same how the a biological
system could coopt exactly the same
computational structure to just check
correctness of very complicated opinions
not just binary
classification how about yakob um a last
thought and then we'll just each have a
closing word
here yeah I'm trying to
connect these thoughts
to
um I guess the the active inference
formalism where like where how many how
many layers of of metacognition do you
need to um to re to realize or uh elicit
this type of self self-reflective
behavior on the different systems that
you're modeling to all of them right
this would be used
everywhere like crazy right you could
use this over and over and over and over
over and over right to check every
single
component right it has no intelligence
so therefore it can be used right
anywhere that's what I'm saying that
that this is the thing that I find
fascinating about it because it has no
intelligence and it's stripped the
semantics you can insert the instrument
anywhere to check statistics of
correctness
of your noisy
oracles what that makes me think about
is uh Chris fields's recent course and
not not not saying you watch this or
anything like that but what he spoke to
was that there's a classical screen that
can be digitized a physical screen and
then there's two agents that have these
semantic reference frames that was done
in a basian statistical setting and you
have kind of um added discret
beads to some first approximation inside
some of these otherwise distributional
considerations like if the two
thermometers can be from 0 to 10 that's
how many parse observations there are
you can have all kinds of distributions
and flows and that type of modeling and
continuous State spaces or there may be
a whole variety of activities available
in the discrete Cube including these
things like well one over and seven up
and then that correlation again to make
the point clear it can be basically
detected and and triangulated where
discret differential is occurring in
active inference we have the kind of
continuous optimization machine learning
but this is more like pinpoint like this
bolt is failing rather than like there's
a08 that one of the bolts is
loose no it's this this is
failing yes it's it's definitely trying
to identify this is failing don't pay
attention it right maybe take it out of
the
emble what are the next steps for your
work
so
the so kind of going through the binary
case has made me realize it was very
hard to figure out the binary case I
I've been working it since
2010 but now that I've finally gone
through the other end and I made and I
figured out how to make it simple I'm
starting to be able to write down what
the solutions have to be for the three
label case so the R equals 3 test and so
what I've not going into is that H it
goes back to that issue of these two
numbers being the same 34 and
35 there's no more information in the
binary case but in the in the three Lael
case you would find that these three
things are not the same right so
strangely enough when you have more
responses there's more information
because there's more chance of
disagreement and disagreement is the
most informative thing that you can have
for an
ensemble agreement is
useless agreement is a tiny portion of
these equations right look at these
equations these equations there are four
of them right well not this one but in
the in the eight one you can see
it yeah the max informative coin flip is
50/50 that's the statistical way to say
this right but here right there are
eight equations and only two of them are
when they completely agree and this is
what people like to talk about platonus
and Tom Mitchell talk about the
agreement equations where they just
wanted to talk about 41 plus 48 add it
and I'm like why why not look at the
full set of information is available
when you consider 41 42 43 40 you know
what I'm saying each one of these is
true it's much more complicated when you
have correlation then you have pawise
correlation and then you have three-way
correlation but my point is right that
these things are are are quite
complicated and but but they have a very
predictable
structure this makes me think about it
being a meta
observation yes it's a second level it's
an
actual alith it's an actual fact as much
as the thermometer reading is a fact the
thermometer that measures the difference
between them is also a
fact that's right and then you have to
decide well I know that I'm in this
domain and you know this is temperature
and temperature is not going to change
very quickly because it's a car engine
right so it can't actually fluctuate you
know what I'm saying that kind of thing
so if you see something that's
fluctuating too much you know that it's
wrong right that's domain knowledge
right being applied to then take a
measurement right and then interpreting
that measurement as being a a a safety
issue or not
right again the computer is needed right
the thermometer is providing the reading
but the computer is needed to understand
why the other analogy I like to make is
like a murder mystery a crime has been
committed with this method you can
interview all the suspects and find VIA
logical consistency the suspect right
because they have a story that doesn't
compare to anybody
else but you cannot find why and how
because there's no semantics of why
people commit murders or how they commit
them right so this helps you solve the
crime who committed the crime you know
this this algorithm is malfunctioning
but it cannot help you figure out
why or how right that you need a higher
cognition
right thank you again for joining thank
you for inviting me in this wonderful
discussion indeed perhaps a
67.2 in a
future time yes I touch thank you guys
thank
you